Guide to the George Jarvis Thompson papers, 1906-1957.
Thompson, George Jarvis papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
George Jarvis Thompson papers, 1906-1957.
18-2-1173
George Jarvis Thompson 1886-1957.
6.8 cubic ft.
Correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes student and professional papers from several schools and travels.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of law.
George Jarvis Thompson received a B.S. in economics from the University of Pennsylvania in 1909, an LL.B. from Harvard University in 1912 and an S.J.D. in 1918. From 1914-1917 he taught Anglo-American Law at Peiyang University, now Tianjin University in Tianjin China. While there he was admitted to the bar of the United States extraterritorial court for China. In 1917 Thompson served as one of the blind-folded drawers of draft numbers for the first draft in World War I. He was appointed Thayer Teaching Fellow at Harvard, 1918-1919, also practicing in Boston with public utility law firms. From 1919-1926, he held a professorship at the University of Pittsburgh, and then went to Cornell University where he taught courses in Procedure, and later in Contracts and Business Regulation. Thompson made his chief contribution to the field as associate editor of the eight-volume REVISED EDITION OF WILLISTON ON CONTRACTS, 1936-1938. At Cornell, he was also active in the American Association of University Professors, Phi Kappa Phi, and the Cornell-in-China program. Thompson's wife Ruth served as the Secretary of the American Red Cross Committee in China during their stay in China.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection includes student papers from the University of Pennsylvania and Harvard Law School; lecture notes, passports, and correspondence (including a chart of Chinese kinship nomenclature and law diagrammed by a student) from Thompson's tenure at Pei Yang (Tianjin) University in Tientsin (Tianjin), China; correspondence and other papers relating to the Cornell University Law School, with letters from former students, some of whom were serving in the Armed Forces in World War II; correspondence, bills, and legal papers relating to a textbook on contract law on which he collaborated with Professor Samuel Williston; papers and articles by Thompson, including "Introductory Lectures in Procedure," 1934; personal correspondence, and correspondence about Indian relics which Thompson collected and cases involving Indian land claims. Also, diplomas and certificates.
Additional photographs and letters relating to the Thompsons' trip to China, and a typescript Report on the Condition of the Military and Civil Prisoners of War in Siberia by R.A. Burr, dedicated to Ruth Thompson.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Thompson, George Jarvis, 1886-1957.; Burr, R. A.; Thompson, Ruth Warren Barnes.; American Red Cross. Committee in China for the Relief of Prisoners of War in Siberia.; Cornell Law School.; Cornell University -- Faculty.; Harvard University -- Students.; Pei Yang University.; Tianjin da xue.; University of Pennsylvania -- Students.
Subjects:
Contracts.; Indians of North America -- Antiquities -- Private collections; Indians of North America -- Land tenure.; Kinship (Law) -- China.; Law -- Study and teaching -- Great Britain.; Law -- Study and teaching -- United States.; Military service, Compulsory.; World War, 1939-1945.; College teachers.; Law teachers.
Places:
China -- Education.; Tianjin (China)
Form and Genre Terms:
Lecture notes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical Information
Box 1
Series II. Correspondences
Box 1-3,6-7
Business Correspondence
Personal Correspondence
Correspondence with Students
University Correspondence and Materials
Miscellaneous Correspondence
Series III. Lecture Notes and Materials
Box 3,6
Series IV. Papers, Publications, and Speeches
Box 3
Series V. Legal Materials
Box 3,6
Series VI. Notes
Box 4-5
Series VII. Family Materials
Box 3,6, Mapcase Folders
Series VIII. Photos
Box 8,Mapcase Folders
Series IX. Certificates, Awards
Mapcase Folders
Series X. Miscellany
Box 3,6
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical Information
  - Articles by and about George J. Thompson (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains "Glimpses of China Days" by Prof. Thompson, and news report "Dr. Thompson Gives Summer Law Courses"
  - Biographical Data of Prof. Thompson (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Materials collected for the Sixth Edition of Who Knows-and What, Directory of American Scholars, and other publications
  - Bibliography of Prof. Thompson's Writings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorial Service for Prof. George J. Thompson, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Correspondences
  - Business Correspondence
    - Admission to the Allegheny County Bar, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - American Machinery and Export Company, Tianjin, China: Correspondences and Materials, 1919-1927 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      Stockholders information
    - Bills, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bills, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bills, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bills, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bills-Revised Edition of Williston on Contracts, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Callaghan & Company Law Publishers, 1939-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Callaghan & Company Law Publishers, 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Congressmen, Letters to, 1935-1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Congressmen, Letters to, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence re Revised Edition of Williston on Contracts (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence re Williston on Contracts, Student's Edition, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Revised Edition of Williston on Contracts-Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Royalty Settlement on Revised Edition of Williston on Contracts-Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Correspondences, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Primarily to Albert W.Ware about personal and family concerns, and descriptions of life in China
    - Correspondences, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondences, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondences, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Letter to Thompson from Chinese friends including Sze Chao Kuei
    - Correspondences, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Letters from Sze Chao Kuei
    - Correspondences, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Letters from Sze Chao Kuei about scholarship aid for Chinese students
    - Correspondences, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Letters from Charles S. Thompson about economic situation in Far East
    - Correspondences, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Correspondence GJT and H.K. Chang about Chinese rugs; pamphlet from missionary
    - Correspondences, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Letter and photo from Yui Ming (Mung Yee Yap) about Law School of Soochow
    - Correspondences, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Correspondences with Yui Ming (Mung Yee Yap), Cornell-in-China materials
    - Correspondences, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Cornell-in-China acknowledgment
    - Correspondences, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Correspondence with Sze Chao Kuei about political events in Europe and the Far East
    - Correspondences, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Letters from C.G Marshall, United Sated News about a possible article by Thompson
    - Correspondence, 1927-1950 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Correspondences, 1914-1917 (Box 6)
      China Letters from George and Ruth Barnes Thompson
    - Correspondences during Stay in China, 1914-1915 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondences during Stay in China, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondences during Stay in China, 1915-1916 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Correspondences during Stay in China, 1915-1916 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondences during Stay in China, 1915-1916 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Contained in a small box
    - Correspondences during Stay in China, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Correspondences during Stay in China, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Contained in a small box, letters and telegrams
    - Correspondences, etc., 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Correspondences, 1919-1926 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Knott Memorial, 1944-1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Contains correspondence with George H. Knott, James C. Knott, etc.
    - Malott, Deane. Former President of Cornell University, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Willcox, Walter, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Williston, Samuel 1, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Samuel Williston was an American lawyer and law professor
    - Williston, Samuel 2, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Williston, Samuel 3, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Williston, Samuel 4, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Williston, Samuel 5, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Williston, Samuel 6, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Williston, Samuel 7, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Williston, Samuel 8, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Williston, Samuel, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Williston, Samuel, 1940-1951 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1922-1948 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1925-1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1944-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Students
    - Former Students, 1932-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Former Students, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Former Students, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Former Students, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - W.W.II-Correspondence with Former Students, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - W.W.II-Correspondence with Former Students, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letters from Students-China, 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - University Correspondence and Materials
    - Cornell Law School, 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Cornell Law School, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15-a)
    - Cornell University-Appointments and Salary, 1926-1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cornell University-Law Faculty Deanship and Recruitment, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Cornell University-Miscellany (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Harvard University. Class of 1912, 1942-1950 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Harvard University. Class of 1912, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Hastings College of Law, Dean David E. Snodgrass, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Pennsylvania, University of. Class of 1909, 1939-1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Pittsburgh, University of, 1919-1941 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Correspondences, 1913-1919 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondences, 1921-1929 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondences, 1930-1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondences, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondences, 1933-1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondences, 1940-1943 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondences, 1943-1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondences, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondences, 1950-1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondences, 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Letters of Introduction, Miscellany-China, 1914-1920 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Letters of Tribute to Prof. Thompson, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III. Lecture Notes and Materials
  - Lecture notes-China 1 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Lecture notes-China 2 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Lecture notes-China 3 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Lecture notes-China 4 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - History of the Courts, 1932-1936 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - History of the Courts, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Indian Cases (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Indian Relics and History, 1939-1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Excerpts (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV. Papers, Publications, and Speeches
  - Publications 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Legislative Acts and Public Documents relating to the University of Pittsburgh, Complied by Prof. Thompson, 1923; "The Relation of Common Carrier of Goods and Shipper, and its Incidents of Liability"; "Challenging Frontiers", 1944.
  - Publications 2 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    "Glimpse of China Days"; "The Next Step in Public Utility Regulation"; "Respective Rights of Preferred and Common Stockholders in Surplus Profits"
  - Valuable Papers and Correspondences (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Student Papers, 1906-1918 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Prof. Thompson's papers and grades as a student
  - Papers by Prof. Thompson (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Legal Education at the mid-century" by Prof. Thompson (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Prof. Thompson's Speech "An Oriental Odyssey", 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series V. Legal Materials
  - Copyright (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Materials on the copyright of Prof. Thompson's publications
  - Contract with Pei-yang University, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Contracts for Williston on Contracts, 1933-1943 (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Series VI. Notes
  Mostly bound volumes of class notes taken while a student at Harvard Law.
  - Bankruptcy by Professes Samuel Williston, 1911-1912 (Box 4)
    Prof. Thompson's class notes during his study in Harvard University Law School
  - Bills and Notes by Professor Joseph D. Brannen, 1910-1911 (Box 4)
  - Class Notes taken in Professor Roscoe Pound's Lectures, 1917-1918 (Box 4)
  - Common Carrier and Public Service Companies by Professor Bruce Wyman Vol. II, 1911-1912 (Box 4)
    Notes taken in Harvard Law School
  - Common Law Procedure, Prof. Thompson (Box 4)
  - Conflicts of Laws by Professor Joseph Beal, 1911-1912 (Box 4)
  - Conflicts of Laws by Professor Joseph Beal Vol.II, 1911-1912 (Box 4)
  - Constitution Law by Prof. Eugene Wambaugh, 1911-1912 (Box 4)
    Notes taken Harvard University Law School
  - Conveyancing in Pennsylvania by Mr. Stern of the Philadelphia Bar, 1912 (Box 4)
  - International Law by Professor Westergard, 1917-1918 (Box 4)
  - Introduction to Law by Hutchins, 1927-1928 (Box 5)
  - Law of Trusts by Professor Roscoe Pound Vol. II, 1911-1912 (Box 5)
  - New York Practice (Box 5)
  - New York Practice Vol. II (Box 5)
  - Private Corporations by Professor Edward H. Warren Vol.I, 1911-1912 (Box 5)
  - Private Corporations by Professor Edward H. Warren Vol.III, 1911-1912 (Box 5)
  - Public Service Companies by Professor Bruce Wyman (Box 5)
  - Roman Law by Professor Roscoe Pound, 1917-1918 (Box 5)
  - Surety-ship and Mortgages by Professor Bruce Wyman, 1911-1912 (Box 5)
  - Trusts by Professor Roscoe Pound (Box 5)
- Series VII. Family Materials
  - Letters from China by Ruth Barns Thompson, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - China-Writings (Box 6, Folder 33)
    Contains The Bell of Peking and Others (a short story collection), "Glimpses of China Days" by George Jarvis Thompson, and My Chinese Honeymoon by Ruth Barnes Thompson
  - Ruth B. Thompson Diary 1, Dec 1914-Jan 1916 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Ruth B. Thompson Diary 2, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Contains account of trip to Peking in April, Shan Hai Wan trip in August, and Red Cross work
  - Ruth B. Thompson Diary 3, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Simmons Female College: Bachelor Degree diploma of Ruth Warren Barns, June 14, 1861 (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Series VIII. Photos
  - Law College Baseball Team, 1908 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - DVD:Pictures taken by George J. and Ruth Barnes Thompson at Pei Yang University While teaching Anglo-American Law, Tianjin, China, 1915-1917; 787, 788 (Box 8)
  - China Photos 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - China Photos 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - China Photos 3 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - China photos, postcards, Train Time Table, and Stanley Club Program (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - China Photo Album: "Xmas Greetings from China" (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photos of the Summer Palace, Peking, China, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Photo Album (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Contains photos taken in Hawaii, China, Japan, Korea, and San Fransisco
  - Photo Album (Box 8, Folder 8)
    With Notes in the Front
  - "Rail Trip Home through the Canadian Rockies", July, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Framed photo of Miyajima, Japan (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Landscape Photo of an Unidentified Place (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Negative Album 1 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Mostly taken in China
  - Negative Album 2 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Negative Album 3 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Glass Plates, Mostly Taken in China (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Photos of Prof. Thompson (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, Postcards, and Films (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Group photo, Pei Yang University with George Thompson, 1916 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Basketball team, 1913 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous interior photograph, Undated (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Series IX. Certificates, Awards
  - Cornell University Phi Kappa Phi: Membership Certificate (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - United State of America District of New Jersey: Certificate as an Attorney and Proctor, December 16, 1913 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts: Certificate of Admission, July 18, 1918 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - United States of America, Southern District of New York: Certificate as Attorney, Proctor, Solicitor, Counsellor and Advocate of the District Court of the United State, July 20, 1914 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Sigma Phi Epsilon Fraternity: Certificate of Penna Delta Chapter, May 14, 1908 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    George J. Thompson is elected and initiated into the Penna Delta Chapter
  - The State of New Jersey: Appointment as an Attorney at Law and Solicitor in Chancery, December 13, 1913 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - University of Pennsylvania: Bachelor of Science in Economics Certificate, June 16, 1909 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Mount Holly State of New Jersey: Certificate of Graduation, June 7, 1906 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Harvard University, LB Degree diploma, June 10, 1912 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Harvard University, JD Degree diploma, June 10, 1913 (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Series X. Miscellany
  - Miscellany, 1917-1948 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Published items by American in China, Peking Fellowship of Reconciliations, Cornell in China, Information collected on China's Legal System and Trade, etc.
  - Miscellany (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Contains Journals and correspondences, materials on American College Club Reunion, etc.
  - Newspaper Clippings about China (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Miscellany (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Contains a checkbook, United State Court for China Decennial Anniversary Brochure, and an account book
  - Miscellany, 191 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Contains account books, My Chinese Honeymoon by Ruth B. Thompson, etc.
  - Menus from Yeiko Maru (a Japanese ocean liner owned by Nippon Yusen Kaisha), 1917 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Postcards from China, Japan, Canada (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Miscellany (Box 6, Folder 22)
    Contains Introductory Lectures in Procedure by George J. Thompson (Revised Edition), and Certificate of Membership of the Delta Theta Phi Law Fraternity
  - Correspondence and report (Box 6, Folder 23)
    Contains Correspondences between Ruth B. Thompson and American Red Cross, and "Report on Condition of Military and Civil Prisonere of War in Siberia"
  - Miscellaneous Program Invitations, etc. (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - W.W.I Materials, 1918-1921 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Passports-China, 1914-1917 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Cornell Daily Sun Questionnaire, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Account Book, 1936-1957 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Prescriptions, correspondences, 1914-1915 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Prof. Thompson's class schedule (1916-1917), Pei Yang University Examination Criminal Law (1917),Stanley Club and American College Club programs, etc.